# Jeff Akins

- San Diego, CA
  (Open to Remote/Travel)
- **720-936-2760**
- jeffakins21@gmail.com
- in linkedin.com/in/jeffakinsmba/
  - github.com/jeffakins

#### **SKILLS AND PROFICIENCIES**

- Python, SQL, Spark, Tableau, Microsoft Suite, Jupyter, Git
- Pandas, Numpy, Seaborn, Matplotlib, Math/Stats, Scikit-Learn, Statsmodels, SciPy, NLP, Beautiful Soup
- Leadership, Teamwork, Bias for Action, Visual Storytelling, Understanding Business Goals, Thinking Strategically

#### **EDUCATIONAL BACKGROUND**

# **Data Science Certificate**

Codeup - Data Science Program Dec 2021

#### **Master of Business Administration**

W. P. Carey School of Business Arizona State University May 2020

#### **Bachelor of Arts in Mathematics**

University of Colorado at Boulder May 2008

# **Executive Summary**

An analytical thinker with experience in management, project coordination, business analytics, data science, and collaborating within a large organization. An adaptable self-starter with a deep interest in utilizing Data Science to achieve business goals. Thoroughly enjoys working with diverse teams to solve complex problems and answering hard questions using data.

#### **RECENT MACHINE LEARNING PROJECTS**

# **Electric Vehicle Charging Infrastructure Growth**

Time Series Modeling

The world's methods of transportation are evolving, not only here in the United States, but globally. This project examined the underlying Electric Vehicle Charging infrastructure, as tracked by the EPA, to analyze the current number of charging stations throughout the U.S., how that number has grown over the past decade, and then forecasted the growth of the charging network through 2023. The Holt-Winters Exponential Smoothing Model produced the best results forecasting that more than 38k EV chargers would be added by the end of 2023. Data visualization techniques were then used to display the historic and predicted growth over time.

# **Examining the Impact of COVID-19 on the Texas Job Market**

Clustering + Time Series

This project explored the impact of COVID-19 on the Texas job market. 98 Industries were examined using a combination of U.S. Census data and Texas Labor Market Information. Clustering analysis was used to group the industries into seven categories based on the magnitude of their job loss during the first half of 2020. For the industries that were most affected, subcategories were examined such as gender, age group, education, race, and ethnicity. Time Series modeling was then used to forecast when select industries would return to pre-COVID levels of employment.

#### **Predicting GitHub Coding Languages**

Classification Modeling + NLP

This project involved predicting the primary coding language used in a GitHub Repository by examining the contents of the corresponding Readme file. Python's Beautiful Soup library was used along with GitHub's API to extract the Readmes. Then the files were cleaned by removing html syntax, stop words, and lemmatizing. Multiple classification models were used, with word type and document length as features, to predict the coding language with an 84% accuracy on out-of-sample data (10% over baseline).

#### **MBA Capstone Project**

# **Business Strategy Simulator**

Ten-week team project managing all decision aspects of a simulated global athletic footwear company to include workforce compensation/training, production facilities, warehouse operations, internal/wholesale marketing, corporate social responsibility, finance, and cash flow. Created a deep understanding of revenue-cost-profit relationships and demonstrated the value of collecting and utilizing business data and reporting to drive decision making. Achieved the 4th highest top end revenue and 4th highest net profit margins out of 12 teams.

# **Jeff Akins**

# **Professional Experience**

# Business Relationship Manager | JP Morgan Chase & Co | Oct 2020 - May 2021

- Self-motivated and proactive Increased JPMC's deposit base by over \$1.2M through managing a portfolio of business clients, building relationships, and providing financial advice focused on client experience, lending, payment services, and risk management.
- Empathized with Clients Helped over 45 small businesses navigate and receive Paycheck Protection Program (PPP) loans during the COVID-19 shutdowns.

#### Senior Aviation Operations Analyst (TS/SCI) | U.S. Central Command | USMC | Nov 2019 - Sept 2020

- Experience answering big picture questions Tracked the status of hundreds of aviation and missile defense assets and analyzed the aviation operations conducted by U.S. and coalition partners throughout the Middle East. Briefed the U.S. Central Command Operations division's General Officers (C-Suite) and staff daily on significant trends thereby informing their strategic decision-making process.
- Developed quantitative analysis, tools, and ad hoc reports Led a project that created a new database for tracking
  the movements of hundreds of military aircraft in over 14 countries throughout the Middle East, which improved
  the strategic planning process for aviation assets as well as the speed of communication within the Joint
  Operations Center. Projected manpower time savings of 12 hours per week once implemented.

#### Program Manager / Aviation Controller Instructor | Training Group Pacific | USMC | Jan 2018 - Oct 2019

- Cultivates an inclusive culture that supports learning Effectively coached, trained, and evaluated the technical performance of over 200 student controllers on how to integrate aviation assets with military ground operations.
- Can navigate ambiguity, prioritize tasks, and execute in a fast-paced environment Led and managed the Air Operations for nine large scale training events resulting in all qualified students graduating. Each event involved two months of planning, was executed over a five-day period, and involved over 40 aircraft and 150 personnel.
- Seeks solutions that are in the clients' best interests Designed and implemented a new aircraft flow schedule that utilized 42% less fixed wing aircraft while still maintaining a 100% training completion rate.
- Ownership of end-to-end analytics Scheduled, tracked, and managed the sourcing and delivery of over 4,500 pieces of aviation ordnance to over 20 squadrons that were located throughout the Southwest U.S.

# Liaison Officer / Analyst | Special Purpose Task Force | USMC | Manama, Bahrain | Nov 2016 - Dec 2017

• Experience working independently and as a member of a cross-functional team – Ensured constant and accurate communication between two large organizations, consisting of over 150 personnel each, through briefings, meetings, writings, data analysis, cultural awareness, and in person and virtual relationship building.

#### Aviation Integrator / Project Manager | Liaison Company | USMC | Oct 2015 - Oct 2016

Ability to influence – Led over 24 highly specialized Marines as the officer in charge, ensuring that they were
trained in their role and could function as a team. Successfully planned, organized, and completed seven smallscale and two large-scale training exercises involving ground logistics and aviation assets. Managed goals,
timelines, logistics, and personnel.

# F/A-18 Pilot | Marine Fighter Attack Squadron 314 | USMC | Jan 2009 - Sept 2015

- A quick and resourceful learner that takes initiative and can adapt to new information Successfully planned and flew over 540 missions; piloting the F/A-18 Fighter Attack Aircraft within the United States in training and overseas to include combat operations in support of Operation Inherent Resolve in Iraq.
- Attention to detail Led and managed the squadron's administration department. Directly supervised eight
  personnel that supported over 200 squadron personnel in all administrative matters to include: personnel pay,
  managing \$1.25M in travel expenditures, monitoring government credit cards, editing daily correspondence, and
  writing over 87 awards.